last time we discussed about
multilingual ASR and then they see the
kind of lot of potential or actually
kind of a lot of benefits of using the
end to end ASR for the MultiLing spe
applications and then at that time I
mentioned that the uh the this is than
to the uh the S item uh it's uh can be
we can build a speech
without expert knowledge uh in this Cas
is the the
the uh the the dictionary right and yes
that it is not easy to get a dictionary
and in this case uh we actually cannot
easily build speech condition for some
uh specific languages so this is what we
learned last time but actually uh this
kind of property always has a pro and
cons and the uh what I didn't explain
the last time was that actually this
classical speech pipeline is not very
bad for the Ming or spe condition so
please check uh this kind of pipeline
again feure extraction acoustic
modeling um sorry yes fure extraction
acoustic modeling re language modeling
and the special this Le comp part is a
kind of a difficult for some languages
and then uh end to end actually making
it simple by using a single model so
that we don't have to use lexicon that
is kind of one of the benefit we have
explained
before
however um we to train speech system in
such kind of a other methodology we
always have to have a pair data of the
speech and corresponding uh
transcriptions to uh build speech
condition and so on so English cases
again it's easy or and the w we can
easily prepare but if we are moving to
very other minor low resource
languages even it is just very difficult
to prepare the PA data and then how to
make
it and actually one of the approach is
using this part form or horum
representation so this is actually
langage independent if using some kind
of
standardized the language independent
phone representation like the IPA
international phone Association based
the pH the symbol and so on and then the
we can actually separate the problem
first from here to here speech to p
p uh this can be any language right uh
the phone uh the does not specify the
languages so uh we first actually makeer
uh the the the acoustic model by only
using the speech and corresponding form
and it's any languages that the English
or Japanese or Mandarin or Hindi or
whatever uh we just kind of combine and
always you know instead of making this
as a Target always using phone as a
Target
and then we can actually building this
acoustic model part
right and then lexan yes we just using
the help from the linguist they actually
are actively working on try to make this
the lexon for many of the minor the Lis
of language and so on it's not easy to
the collect the data but it's not
difficult to investigate and provide
making a a Leon so there are actually
lot of resources for many languages for
the Leon
part and then after that this part let
to the language model we only require
the text data right so by using uh this
kind of methodology we could actually uh
build uh the speech conition for some
specific languages without using the
parallel data
so in these cases again that we just are
they they using the machine learning at
the Deep neural network to build acostic
models get the help from the the
linguist there are lot of kind of the
the people actually building such kind
of Lex for many of the languages and
then if we have some kind of a there
Text data we can also building the
language model and then without using
the pair data we could actually making
the speech
system so this is actually one of the
the CMU work and the uh with this kind
of methodology uh can you guess how many
languages we can now deal with I say we
cannot you know wholy making it but it's
with this kind of a methodology we can
make it the possible and now we are
building the the the the massive
multilingual speech conition and how
many language is that do you think that
we are dealing
with actually next slide has some answer
so please do not check it or people
checking it do not
answer do you guys guess how many okay
so hint that we have usually have
7,000 uh languages or 8,000 language
depending on who counts and the
commercial prop uh the product probably
up to around
100 and the methods are the massive
multilingual speech which are the they
claim to kind of De dealing with the 1,
langages okay the other I can give you
the answer the answer is that we
actually that uh try to handle 2,000
languages yeah exactly more exactly
1900 1 n z05 or something like that so
uh this is again that by using the uh
this methodology and also uh this is not
only our effort a lot of the linguist
and so on actually the making the great
resources and then by collecting this we
could actually handle to the deal with
2,000 language
is but of course you know this is not
perfect uh since we don't have enough
data and so on by the way even we cannot
test it uh because the most cases we
actually don't have audio data and just
you know lexicon and some kind of a part
of the text data and then we build it so
we are not sure this kind of language is
it really working and so on uh but
anyway by using this kind of the project
uh
Direction uh we are actually dealing
with
2000 the
languages uh and uh by the way we cannot
uh extend from 2000 to more languages
even we have our 7,000 languages can you
know that why we cannot extend anymore
do you know the answer for
this it's actually quite the
obvious uh up to
2000 some languages have
script but the L of the 5,000 languages
only spoken languages so if for example
we use you know the Ping P that we could
Define the ASR task but generally since
they don't have a script so we actually
even cannot Define the speech con for
these languages so this the 5,000
language is probably we should try to
map it to the phone symbol or we try to
use a speech translation and then the
the converting to the some of the other
languages that will be probably we can
do for the rest of the 5,000
languages and again we are actually
actively uh working on this the mingal
speech the problems in addition to this
work we also recently uh the launched
the new uh the The Benchmark which is
mingal speech processing Universal
performance Benchmark uh the ml Spar and
I will actually explain bit about this
The Spar project later if I have time
but this is a kind of
extended version of the SP pro project
for the multilingo side and this is not
aligned with this one this is more for
the N2 and ASR side but we actually are
the working on the 100 starting from the
143 language as a benchmark and then now
expanding it
154 and gradually making this to the
very large number to the cover uh the
many of the languages our the research
uh and the development other the
platforms okay so uh that's the the the
rest of the part that I I couldn't
explain it but anyway the MultiLing ASR
uh the uh there are kind of a lot of
activities now but mostly these kind of
activities are not only from the the
speech researchers it's also from the
lot of uh the the uh the contribution uh
in the the language SES and then we can
actually making the significant advance
in this kind
multilingual error and the I explained
the uh multilingual as as a kind of the
can be one of the simple uh direction of
just mixing everything and then doing
the uh the the the multilingual speech
condition and then uh I this one but
another trend is actually given this
kind of the multilingual speech part
find tuning is actually another
possibility which I will explain if I
have time uh in today's meeting uh
today's uh the lecture and the uh uh
this uh the the uh the direction is
again there are lot of difficulties in
data uh just finding the data is
difficult even we find the data some of
the data has a sensitive kind of
information or the license and so on the
correction is also very important and
the data is quite noisy in these cases
so the the the cleaning is also the very
difficult uh challenging problem and the
again our team is not only just building
the speech uh recognition for the many
languages we are actually also working
on the this uh data collection uh part
as well so that's the about the mingal
speech condition any
questions okay sounds good and then move
to the today's
part uh just uh let me show you some
introduction of today's part and then
would like to pass it to the
so today I will talk about the second
part of the the Advan Topic in n and
ASR and today I will talk about the the
foundation models now you know there are
lot of foundation models in the uh image
uh the text and so on right and the
speech also has a other Foundation
models there are already ongoing
activities for people are also trying to
kind of expand this one and the CMU is
actually working on this area quite
actively and the uh there is actually a
blog post that we recently made for the
uh the foundation uh models so I just
put a link in the uh the um in the
slider uh but anyway uh the yeah we call
it foundation for speech Foundation
models and we just are listing four
items uh which including the MLS P that
I mentioned before and the S supervisor
speech representation that I may explain
it if I have sufficient time and the
data collection part are the the 420k
hours of unated mingal data which I have
mentioned that we are also working on it
and another part is uh
reproducing The Whisper style the speech
models and that is actually one of the
our recent the activities and want to
pass it to the event
yes okay so in this part of the
presentation uh I will introduce one of
our recent efforts towards building a
speech Foundation model
and this model we call the a it stands
for an open disper style speech model
and this is the first large scale speech
Foundation model from the
Academia and I also included a paper
link and a collab demo at the bottom of
this page so if you are interested you
can play with the demo maybe after this
lecture um I will start from the
motivation why we want to build a
Foundation model and why want it to be
open source and then I will introduce
some of the design choices and also um
some of the results uh finally I can
show the demo uh with several
examples if can achieve some interesting
zero short
Behavior so
firstly um I think in our previous
lectures we have uh seen this General
Trend in speech models we are changing
from traditional machine learning to
some deep learning based systems and we
are now more interested in building and
systems um compared to casc
systems and actually that's another
recent Trend that we want to move from
monolingual to multilingual from task
specific to multitask and from some
small model to bigger models that can be
trained on larger
data so this lead to the concept of
speech Foundation model we usually um
refer to this type of model as a
foundational
model um compared to some traditional
approaches the foundational models can
have several
benefits um these are my opinions so
firstly it usually improves the
performance this is mainly because the
model is trained on a more sufficient
data it has a larger capacity because of
the larger motor size and also we are
combining multiple languages and
multiple tasks so we can benefit from
the cross lingual and cross task
knowledge
transfer another benefit is that it's
usually easier to develop and devoid
such a multitask model because we no
longer need to train separate models for
different data for different tasks or
different languages instead we just
combine all the data and train a single
model and this model architecture is
also usually quite a standard we don't
need too much tuning on
it among all these um popular speech
Foundation models I think open as
whisper is probably the most well-known
mind it was released about one year ago
and it already got nearly 800 cations as
of today so for a speech paper this is
already very
amazing um in terms of the architecture
I think there's nothing special it's
just a standard Transformer encoder
decoder which most of you have
implemented in the coding assignment is
basically the same
thing um but it combines multiple Speech
to Text uh conversion tasks including
speech recognition speech translation
language identity ification and out
level
alignment um the difficult theme for
this project is that
um train hug
am lab speech data in the inial version
they use 180,000 hours and recently they
they upgraded to a new version which was
train on 1 million plus 4 million hours
um and this is very huge because like in
the coding assignment before you using
only 100
hours and this one is um maybe 7,000
times
larger um W generally achieves very good
performance especially on the high
resource languages and
tasks um but there are some limitations
in our project we focus on uh one
specific limitation which is um the
Source issue so basically whisper
released the inference code and the
model checkpoints and but we cannot
access their training data we don't know
how they collected data and what are
included in the training
set and we also don't know how to
tra um so this can cause several
concerns firstly if we want to use
visper for our own task especially if we
want to apply it to some new test set we
can easily encounter data leakage issue
because we don't know how the model is
trained on which data it is trained and
this may be um fitting in some
cases and this has become a popular
debate even in the large language model
uh research
Community because they are facing the
same
issue and the second problem is that
um as some of you might know these
models are very large and the training
data is very diverse it combines
multiple tasks and it's usually very
noisy training a model on this typ data
is not an easy
task um so without knowing the training
Dynamics it is very difficult for the
other people to reproduce this type of
work and to further improve the
performance and thirdly um this can
cause some robustness fairness or bias
issue and this is also a very important
problem nowadays and this often comes
from the training process that means we
need to understand how the model is
trained on which data it is trained in
order to improve the robustness fairness
and so
on so inspired by this um we started
this project and we aim to promote
transparency and promote open science in
large scale speech pre-t
training okay uh next I will will talk
about our uh
model uh first I would like to give a
high level overview of our model so it
is an open whisper style speech model
and we train it on a publicly available
ASR and St data
it is implemented in an open source tool
kit ESP spnet and we have released all
the training logs and the training code
um so that others can easily um anal
analyze our uh
model um for the tasks um we basically
follow the design of visper um but for
the model architecture we tried to uh we
tried several modif
ations uh firstly we extended to from
any to English translation to any to any
language
translation um this is quite a
straightforward and the performance
actually depends on the training
data um to improve the efficiency uh we
increased the D sample ratio in the
encoder site this means for a given
input our output lens will be shorter
than the original
whisper and the shorter lens will reduce
the comination in self attention so this
can improve the overall training
efficiency and also we applied as the
hybrid CDC attention training um
think that was introduced in previous
lectures so this can improve the
convergence of the model and also
improves the performance of certain
tasks um
so our model generally achieves good
performance especially for the high
resource languages and tasks and
sometimes it's even better than
whisper but we still need to improve it
on some low resource
tasks um I guess some of you are not
familiar with the visper design so I
will spend some time introduce how the
wher is
designed uh um basically whisper
combines different types of speech to
text tasks in a unified
format and here I'm showing the text
format so that means we have a speech
input and we want to generate this
text in an auto regressive manner uh
this is a standard Auto regressive
decoder or we can call it a language
model it performs some conditional
generation so it models the conditional
probability of the actual transcription
given some uh text
condition
specifically we have a special token
denoting the start of
sentence and we have another special
token
Den in between we concatenate multiples
including
for language t
for the task
and tab only and everything is
concatenated in a single
Dimension and for inference I am showing
one example here um so first we extract
the speech features fit it into the
encoder and we get the encoder outputs
this will be used by the decoder through
cross attention now this is also same as
the coding assignment for for auto
regressive decoding we start from a
special token sosos start of sentence
and then we generate the first
prediction here it is a special tag
denoting the language we want to know
the language of the input
speech and then we append it to the
input so the input now has a length of
two previously is just a single token
and we also attend a special task token
uh which tells the model that we want to
perform speech recognition now and then
it starts to generate the actual
prediction um here we also include the
time stamp this is the start time
stamp for the first
out uh
this and then we
just
process and
generate finally we we will generate an
end of sentence token and we St the
decoding and here you may notice that we
have prettying the time stamps but why
do we need the time stamps it's actually
main used for long form
decoding long form decoding is a bit
different from what we have seen in
previous
lectures so usually we pre- segment or
the data and the input is only a single
ad and but suppose we have a very long
audio say 1 hour long how can we
transcribe
it uh there are several strategies the
simpl strategy might be that we just
throw the input to some free train model
and see what
happens and usually this will cause Auto
memory issue because the motj cannot
handle um this long data and also this
has a mismatch between the train and the
inference during training the model is
usually trained on some short
segments so it cannot generalize well to
the long input at inference
time another approach which is um most
widely used solution right now is to
pre- segment the data and transcribe
each segment and concatenate all the
transcriptions to achieve this we need
to detect a spe versus nonspeech
area uh region so this is called a voice
activity detection it usually works well
yeah but in whisper they adopt a
different approach which is to jointly
predict the time
stamps um so next I will show how we
perform this window inference with
predicted time
information um firstly we have this uh
very long audio and our model is trained
on some short segments like in mixer the
model is trained on 30 second window is
a fix size
window so firstly we just take the first
30 seconds send this into the model and
generate the
hypothesis this hypothesis includes the
start and end Tim stamp for each
utterance um in this first example the
first sentence starts from0 second and
ends at uh around 14 seconds the
following arance starts from 15 seconds
and ends at about
27 now we know when it
ends um we can shift the window based on
this predicted time stamp we just shift
the window to 27
seconds and then continue this decoding
process for the second window we also
generate a h hes with all the time
stamps and we know when it ends we shift
it
again and we get the third window the
third prediction finally to get the full
transcription of the entire input audio
we just conate all the short
segments and this also tells us how the
text is aligned with the uh input audio
in an admin level okay so um for our
experiments
we consider the three setups uh we
gradually increased the data and the
model
size and finally we reached the size of
the whisper media model but our data is
still much
smaller and more efforts are
required um here I'm showing our uh
training
data for the V version we have 38,000
hours
about 22
languages and then we increase um the
data for these high resource languages
mainly for the English
Chinese um so it goes up to more than
100,000 and then we extended to include
more languages um especially for multi
lingual speech recognition and it goes
to about 180,000
um next I will show some results of our
model compared to the over Wisper uh
first result is on English
ASR so the First Column is open whisper
small second colum is the medium and the
following three columns are our three
versions the gray color means that uh
the model performance is better than the
whisper so actually um our model can
achieve reasonable performance in most
of the
benchmarks and is even better than
whisper in select
benchmarks and note that our training
data is only about um 25% a quarter of
the data used for um
whisper so this is already quite
encouraging
result for the multilingual ASR uh
General finding is that the performance
highly correlates with the training data
size for some languages like Japanese we
have sufficient training data so we can
achieve very good performance but for
some languages the training data is very
limited and the performance is not that
good for spee translation uh as I
mentioned before whisper only supports
any to English translation and we extend
it to more translation
directions and the finding is also
similar the performance highly
correlates with the training data
size for some language DET uh directions
we have more than 10,000 hours of data
and we can achieve a reasonable uh
translation
score but in some cases the training
data is very very limited uh so it
almost doesn't
work we also evaluated the model on
language
identification um so that means for a
given input ad we want to classify it
into one of the predefined
languages and our model is actually
quite good performs quite well uh this
is because we support more languages in
the training
data I also included two examples for
the time St
prediction um the input is a fixed
length 30 second audio
segment and we run the model using G
research the First Column is the the
ground TOS from some T talk Corpus and
the second colon is our
prediction um if we compare the two
results uh we can see that the time
stamp is usually
accurate but note that uh utterance is
not a well defined concept so you can
have different definitions for utterance
you can merge some consecutive
utterances to form a longer
atance and also the um time stamp is
usually not that accurate even for the
ground truth it may include some silent
um at the beginning or after some
ADV so considering uh all of these our
performance is quite
good this also means that the model the
decoder actually knows when to generate
a a time stamp token it has the sense of
some timing
information so um I also listed several
future directions um I think there are
mainly maybe three directions first is
to improve the
efficiency um but currently the model is
quite large and inference can be very
slow so how to compress the model uh can
be a very practical
issue and
recently released paper to the still
whisper and it works uh well on ASR task
it can achieve some good uh speed
up and the second direction is to
improve the
performance we can try more advanced
incoder architecture uh we are already
trying this and got some good
results and we can also try some self
superise pre-training to utilize more
data and we also need to inove improve
the training data quality this is a very
important issue
and finally um we need to think about
what we can get from this type of
work like in large language models um
scaling up can give you some benefits
like emerg capabilities but how about uh
for speech can we get something similar
I think all these are not Val